<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Cubic reasoning</title>
<link>https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Thoughtful essays</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:33 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The pursuit of wealth and the enjoyment of life</title>
  <dc:creator>Norman Simon Rodriguez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/wealth_prosperity/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The paradox suggested by this thought, namely, that all the economic process does is to transform valuable matter and energy into waste, is easily and instructively resolved. It compels us to recognize that the real output of the economic process (or of any life process, for that matter) is not the <em>material flow</em> of waste, but the still mysterious <em>immaterial flux</em> of the enjoyment of life.</p>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="georgescu">Georgescu-Roegen (1975)</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Humans are unique in their possession of complex psychological needs alongside material ones. While other animals, like a chimpanzee or a dog, might experience boredom in captivity, their needs are largely physical, centred on survival and well-being. In contrast, humans seek psychologically stimulating activity. Even the earliest hunter-gatherer societies valued symbolic objects like beads and ornaments, establishing wide-ranging trade networks across hundreds of kilometres in Sub-Saharan Africa to acquire them <span class="citation" data-cites="heritage2030144 Crowther03052016">(Koleini et al. 2019; Crowther et al. 2016)</span>. The prevalence of religion and shamanistic beliefs, evidenced by cave paintings around the world, further demonstrates that human needs extend far beyond mere physical preservation.</p>
<p>The very idea of <em>wealth</em> is therefore unusual. If people can live in comfort without a great abundance of goods—that is, without being rich—why has the pursuit of wealth played such a dominant role in culture throughout history? Here, a distinction between prosperity and wealth could be useful. We can define prosperity as possessing sufficient material goods to enjoy lasting material well-being. Wealth, on the other hand, is the accumulation of material goods beyond prosperity—that is, beyond what is needed for a comfortable life. From this distinction it follows that, if prosperity satisfies humanity’s physical needs, the purpose of wealth is not material well-being, but the fulfilment of psychological desires.</p>
<p>Following this logic, <em>poverty</em> can be understood as the lack of prosperity. If there is a moral imperative to reduce poverty, then its goal should be to ensure as many people as possible become prosperous, though not necessarily wealthy. Of course, the accumulation of wealth is just one of many ways people seek psychological fulfilment. Some find it in study, service, spirituality or their work—and for most, satisfaction comes from a combination of these and other pursuits. The danger arises when an individual, or an entire society, continues to pursue wealth long after achieving prosperity. While consumption and investment may stimulate economic activity that benefits those still in poverty, a society that crosses the threshold into mass wealth risks tying its collective sense of well-being to the endless pursuit of luxury. In other words, it risks becoming consumed by greed, a condition where not only the wealthy but also the prosperous and even the poor seek to maximize their possessions at any cost—not to live well, but simply to be rich.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/wealth_prosperity/habit-of-a-wealthy-merchant-of-london-in-1588-riche-marchand-de-londres-2a3ad5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="427"></p>
<figcaption>A wealthy merchant of London (1588). <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Habit_of_a_wealthy_merchant_of_London_in_1588._Riche_marchand_de_Londres_(NYPL_b14140320-1638225).jpg">Source</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Beyond the social harms of a greedy society—where injustice is readily committed for personal gain—lies a more fundamental problem. The earth’s ecosystem has finite resources and a limited capacity to regenerate. When human populations were small, greedy societies like ancient empires endangered their own civilizations but not necessarily the entire planet. Today, however, historic population growth combined with a global tendency to equate psychological satisfaction with material gain has led to a visible and dangerous environmental overload. Theorists like Boulding and Georgescu-Roegen (quoted in the epigraph above) warned of this in the twentieth century, and a growing chorus of scientists and activists has since joined them. The issue is psychological. Just as a desperately thirsty person might knowingly drink contaminated water to satisfy an urgent physical need, a person driven by greed can ignore clear and present dangers to satisfy that psychological compulsion. No amount of scientific evidence or moral reasoning will deter someone who has made the accumulation of wealth a basic psychological necessity. The root of the climate crisis, therefore, appears to be more moral than technical. The widespread refusal to protect the environment and challenge injustices committed in the name of wealth stems not from a failure to understand the evidence, but from a deep-seated unwillingness to accept its implications. To accept the science would mean renouncing what has become for many a primary life purpose: the pursuit of riches.</p>
<p>Resolving this problem is profoundly difficult. Binding political decisions could in theory be taken, such as the measure that successfully phased out chlorofluorocarbons in the late 1980s and prevented the ozone layer from continuing to degrade at the alarming pace it had been <span class="citation" data-cites="velders2007importance">(Velders et al. 2007)</span>. At that time, for nearly twenty years, chemical industries—especially DuPont, the makers of CFCs—resisted regulation tooth and nail, claiming there was no evidence that CFCs were destroying the stratosphere. When the evidence finally became undeniable, governments around the world <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montreal_Protocol">acted</a> with surprising speed and determination. Yet replicating that experience today is far more difficult. Replacing CFCs was relatively straightforward; climate change is not as immediately visible as the ozone hole once was; and fossil fuel industries wield immense lobbying power, reinforced by the fact that many developing countries rely on oil and coal exports for their survival and that of their political elites. Moreover, even if national measures were taken in a democratic country, their effect would at best be negligible (since the largest emitters are non-democratic states) and, at worst, they would be repealed by later governments to placate social discontent over the resulting economic slowdown.</p>
<p>While the world’s future may depend heavily on the actions of major global powers, this does not render individual and local action powerless. We can still do much to live well and help others do so within our own spheres of influence. Above all, we can strive to resist the lure of greed and instead cultivate a more sustainable vision of a prosperous life.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-Crowther03052016" class="csl-entry">
Crowther, Alison, Patrick Faulkner, Mary E. Prendergast, Eréndira M. Quintana Morales, Mark Horton, Edwin Wilmsen, Anna M. Kotarba-Morley, et al. 2016. <span>‘Coastal Subsistence, Maritime Trade, and the Colonization of Small Offshore Islands in Eastern African Prehistory’</span>. <em>Journal of Island and Coastal Archaeology</em> 11 (2): 211–37. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/15564894.2016.1188334">https://doi.org/10.1080/15564894.2016.1188334</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-georgescu" class="csl-entry">
Georgescu-Roegen, Nicholas. 1975. <span>‘Energy and Economic Myths’</span>. <em>Southern Economic Journal</em> 41 (3).
</div>
<div id="ref-heritage2030144" class="csl-entry">
Koleini, Farahnaz, Philippe Colomban, Innocent Pikirayi, and Linda C. Prinsloo. 2019. <span>‘Glass Beads, Markers of Ancient Trade in Sub-Saharan Africa: Methodology, State of the Art and Perspectives’</span>. <em>Heritage</em> 2 (3): 2343–69. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/heritage2030144">https://doi.org/10.3390/heritage2030144</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-velders2007importance" class="csl-entry">
Velders, Guus JM, Stephen O Andersen, John S Daniel, David W Fahey, and Mack McFarland. 2007. <span>‘The Importance of the Montreal Protocol in Protecting Climate’</span>. <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em> 104 (12): 4814–19.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <guid>https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/wealth_prosperity/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:33 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dialogue and coherence as elements of a modern work ethic</title>
  <dc:creator>Norman Simon Rodriguez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/work_ethic/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Although the idea that Calvin was a kind of intellectual originator of capitalism is very popular, the absence in his writings of any mention of the importance of accumulating capital or the notion of ‘salvation through work’ is striking. As a general rule, the authors who portray Calvin as an ideological precursor of the modern economic paradigm do not quote him directly, but do so second-hand through sociological interpretations, especially that of Weber’s celebrated treatise <span class="citation" data-cites="weber2001">(Weber 2001)</span>, who, similarly, also cited him through third parties. As Weber himself warned in his book <span class="citation" data-cites="weber2001">(Weber 2001, 175)</span>,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For the following discussion I may here say definitely that we are not studying the personal views of Calvin, but Calvinism, and that in the form to which it had evolved by the end of the sixteenth and in the seventeenth centuries in the great areas where it had a decisive influence and which were at the same time the home of capitalistic culture.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thus Weber, who was a sociologist and not a theologian, studied the culture of the countries where Calvinism was the dominant branch of Protestantism for two centuries after the Reformation, not specifically the way in which Calvin’s theology might have given rise to the work ethic characteristic of European capitalism. This subtle but important distinction, fortunately, is evident in the work of some authors such as <span class="citation" data-cites="lopez_oneto2016">López Oneto (2016)</span>. That Protestantism and Capitalism are correlated is practically undeniable <span class="citation" data-cites="basten2011">(see, for example, Basten and Betz 2011)</span>, but the specific nature of this relationship is not easy to elucidate. Calvin, as well as Luther, Zwingli, Reina and all the other reformers were much more concerned with denouncing the excesses of Catholicism, printing bibles and laying the foundations for a new Christian morality with a view to the spiritual world than with promoting a new economic system. In this, it can be said that they were theologians, not economists or sociologists. Not even <em>Pilgrim’s Progress</em> <span class="citation" data-cites="bunyan2014">(Bunyan 2014)</span>, considered a buttress of English Puritanism, wastes ink on the work ethic. The few lines it devotes to warning of the dangers of befriending Slothful, a character in the allegory, make clear that he represents not laziness in worldly labor, but negligence in seeking spiritual salvation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/work_ethic/reformation_wall.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The Reformation Wall in Geneva"></p>
<figcaption>The Reformation Wall in Geneva. Source: Nikolai Karaneschev (<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Geneve_-_panoramio_(38).jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The misinterpretation of religious cultures, including the work ethics with which they are associated, is also evident in post-deistic Marxism and in its dictum of religion as the ‘opium’ of the masses, as an emergency anaesthetic, as a means of escape from a dreadful reality produced by labour exploitation. Religion, in the caricature born of Marx’s inventiveness, would be a feeble invention of weak minds, which, if extirpated, no matter with what violence, would not cause great harm to individuals or to society, but rather ‘real happiness’.<sup>1</sup> An idea later taken up by the Soviet and Chinese authoritarian regimes with the nuance that religion would be, in addition to a painful psychological need of the oppressed, a device of power invented by the oppressors.</p>
<p>Traditional economics presents an equally reductionist conception, expressed in the neoclassical idea of the human being, in this context the worker, as <em>homo oeconomicus</em>, by nature a maximiser of individual utility, rational, normally possessing perfect information in competitive environments of homogeneous agents <span class="citation" data-cites="borjas2020 brozova2015 phelps1968 vercherand2014">(Borjas 2020, esp.&nbsp;chaps. 2, 4 and appendix; Brožová 2015; Phelps 1968; Vercherand 2014)</span>. Whereas in Marx the conceptual reduction lies in his understanding that self-realisation is almost exclusively a function of work<sup>2</sup> (and this not from an individual but from a collective, urban, homogenising, despotic and class-based morality), in the case of the neoclassicals the reduction consists in that all human decisions, including moral ones, can be understood as scenarios of optimisation under constraints according to the rules of individualistic and utilitarian economic rationality, with the consequent denial of the social injustices that the blind application of this theory engenders <span class="citation" data-cites="bedoya2021 kaltenbrunner2018">(Bedoya Dorado and Peláez León 2021; Kaltenbrunner and Painceira 2018)</span>.</p>
<p>With religious discourse annulled by the Enlightenment in European academic circles, the search for non-moralistic intellectual horizons has gradually led to the omission, or at least the obscuring, of the moral considerations of individuals in the world of work and outside of it. It is implicitly assumed that people work either out of necessity, obligation, or greed, but, with the exception of some disciplines such as occupational psychology <span class="citation" data-cites="dik2007">(see, for example, Dik and Duffy 2007)</span>, the ethical (and even religious) dimension that the act of working comprises for many people is not usually made visible. For example, the decision of which trade to choose is not exclusively based on a calculation of economic returns, however much these may have a role in weighing up the opportunity costs. Motivated by their personal convictions, and limited by their circumstances, a person may decide to become a police officer, or a doctor, or a musician, or a priest, or a scientist. Some people set out to become managers or entrepreneurs, and feel deeply that this is their professional calling in life. Beyond choosing a profession, individuals also make other work-related decisions guided by their moral considerations. Decisions about how many hours to devote to work versus personal development, how diligently to perform their tasks, and how humanely to treat subordinates are just a few examples. Although less skilled workers may have fewer options, they remain moral agents. To claim that their views on life do not influence their actions—because they are supposedly dictated entirely by scarcity—is to ignore a fundamental aspect of their humanity.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/work_ethic/ward.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><a href="https://jenikirbyhistory.getarchive.net/amp/media/first-ward">First ward, Ontario, Canada, 1890.</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A central element of the Protestant ethic—and this one was indeed fervently promoted by Calvin and Luther, and by the English-speaking traditions, from the Quakers in England to the black revivalists of Azusa Street—is the emphasis on argumentation as the basis of social understanding. If in the Middle Ages belief in papal dogmas was a prerequisite for taking part in any conversation, in the era of the Reformation, religious belief was a consequence of the careful examination of biblical texts and of rational argumentation, an exercise that aimed to unveil truths without the intrusion of forced or arbitrary creeds (<em>sola scriptura</em>). Additionally, coherence was expected between what was preached and what was practised (the evidence of <em>sola fide</em> was good works, not the mere formalism of penance<sup>3</sup>). Protestant proselytism, from its very theological basis, sought to convince the unconverted through preaching and exemplary behaviour, which placed it a world away from the ideology of Catholicism. It is no coincidence that Kant, the great proponent of the use of practical reason (complemented, of course, by pure reason), was raised in a Lutheran household. Even the Frankfurt School, so distant from the Reformation in time and temper, is not detached from this conception that has been part of the German intellectual spirit since Luther put forward his theses at the University of Wittenberg and at the Diet of Worms <span class="citation" data-cites="luther1957">(Luther 1957)</span>.</p>
<p>It is worth pausing to reflect on these two features of the temperament of the Protestant ethic (that is, argumentation and coherence). Based on their own personal experience, someone might conclude, <em>à la Marx</em>, that the social relationship between the employee and the business owner is inherently and inevitably conflictive. Another person, with leanings towards neoclassical economics, might simply argue that the relationship is not conflictive because it does not exist, since employment would not be a social activity but a by-product of market forces and human needs <span class="citation" data-cites="bedoya2021">(see Bedoya Dorado and Peláez León 2021, who address this notion from the point of view of the gig economy)</span>. Contrary to what the libertarian right would say, it is evident that employment is in fact a social relationship, but, at the same time, contrary to the opinions of the left, it is not inherently or inevitably conflictive (which, it should be clarified, does not imply denying the existence, so crassly ubiquitous, of exploitation and evil). The hope that agreements can be reached through dialogue and negotiation is not so remote if one turns to the two pillars of argumentation and coherence.</p>
<p>To believe that human beings can talk to one another, listen to one another, and earn each other’s trust by fulfilling their duties does not require unfounded optimism. Good employers exist, just as good employees do—and not only in large, prestigious companies but also in the small establishments typical of less advantaged sectors. The well-being of both employees and employers in a given area depends, then, on the number of good employers as a percentage of the total number of employers, and on the number of good employees as a percentage of the total number of employees. Places where a large proportion of bosses and employees do not fulfil their duty (lacking in coherence) and do not resolve their differences peacefully through dialogue (lacking in argumentation) will be places where there will be discontent, oppression and hardship. The places where the opposite is true will also enjoy higher levels of psychological, and potentially economic, well-being, due in part to the positive effect of trust in reducing transaction costs at the societal level.</p>
<p>An experience that is relevant here is that described by <span class="citation" data-cites="staley1965">Staley and Morse (1965, 76ff)</span> in their reflection on home-based work in France, the United States and Switzerland in the mid-20th century. The industrialisation of the then-developed countries had historically included a stage in which industries worked in a decentralised manner, sending service orders to families (possibly along with raw materials), who used more or less modern machinery to manufacture parts and pieces in their homes, elements that were later sent to the main factory for assembly, finishing and commercialisation. As the same authors state, although the system allowed for greater productive efficiency compared to the more artisanal arrangements of the past, it also gave rise to aberrant abuses by the factories and the suppliers of raw materials. The widespread outcry against the satellite system led these countries to begin to rethink the role of home-based work in their economies. For the French <span class="citation" data-cites="staley1965">(Staley and Morse 1965, 77)</span>, the balance seemed to be tipped towards conserving satellite work, but counterbalanced with soft regulations that would allow efficiency gains to be maintained while at the same time reducing the worst injustices. For American public opinion <span class="citation" data-cites="staley1965">(Staley and Morse 1965, 77–78)</span>, the system was so bad that it had to be eliminated completely. Staley and Morse, on the other hand, offered the alternative of the Swiss model, which included strong regulations to protect the worker, but at the same time, equally strong incentives to promote the best forms of work in the satellite mode. The key point of the policies adopted between 1930 and 1940 was, however, the incorporation of the figure of the ‘benevolent intermediary’, who acted as a mediator of goodwill between the workers and the employers. The federal government, with a determined commitment, helped to ensure that the rules were complied with, and the employees and employers themselves assumed the rules voluntarily as part of a civic commitment. The benevolent intermediary (the <em>Schweizerische Zentralstelle für Heimarbeit</em> or Swiss Central Office for Home Work), a private entity but with government support, was in charge of helping the different parties to come to an agreement peacefully and respectfully, while at the same time strengthening, hand in hand with the Swiss Home Work organisation (<em>Schweizerische Heimatwerk</em>), the job skills of the employees, a large part of whom were rural. The new paradigm brought excellent results in the years following its implementation, both in terms of prosperity and respect for the rights of the workers.</p>
<p>The most important part of the anecdote is that what made the scheme work was largely the ethical commitment of all those involved, that is, their coherence, as well as the diligence shown in reaching mutually satisfactory consensuses through dialogue. In the authors’ words <span class="citation" data-cites="staley1965">(Staley and Morse 1965, 79)</span>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>It must be stressed, however, that three conditions which are present in Switzerland and have helped to make the policy workable are unlikely to be present in many newly industrializing countries. The three conditions are (1) a generally prosperous economy with comparatively high incomes and a high standard of education, which means that workers have alternative opportunities and are not easily exploitable; (2) public administration which is generally efficient and honest, so regulations are enforced; and (3) many citizens who have a high sense of civic spirit and civic obligation, which makes it possible for private associations to take on social tasks and perform them responsibly. This last is particularly important in relation to the most novel element in Swiss policy, which we shall refer to as the role of the benevolent intermediary.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These cultural traits were, without a doubt, a legacy of the Calvinist past of the Swiss <span class="citation" data-cites="basten2011">(Basten and Betz 2011)</span>, including the first one, which comes from the Protestant cultural tradition of educating the population without class distinction.</p>
<p>Of course, it is not the purpose of this essay to propose that the only way to achieve social dialogue is through a particular religion, since religious freedom as a human right must be defended with unwavering determination in any modern democracy. Rather, it is to draw attention to the fact that it is indeed possible to have both prosperous companies and satisfied employees without having to adopt the positions of the poles of the contemporary ideological spectrum. Individuals must be educated from an early age in a work ethic based on dialogue and coherence, in responsibility and respectful coexistence, and the State must guarantee the conditions for these social virtues to flourish, while punishing those people and institutions who oppose dialogue and foment violence, or who fail to comply with labour agreements (whether in their role as employees or as employers). To a large extent, labour policies in Latin America show laudable progress in terms of improving workers’ conditions <span class="citation" data-cites="neffa2014 neffa2011">(Neffa et al. 2014; Neffa 2011)</span>, but an overemphasis on the conflictive dimension carries the risk of overlooking the real solution to the problem, namely, the search for understanding through reasoned communication and the fulfilment of duties towards others. Only through the ethical commitment of many people is it possible to generate real changes in a country’s conditions. This is daunting, certainly, as bringing about major cultural changes in the world is extremely difficult. But at the same time, it is the reality, and as such it should not be ignored.</p>





<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-basten2011" class="csl-entry">
Basten, Christoph, and Frank Betz. 2011. <span>‘Marx Vs. <span>Weber</span>: <span>Does Religion Affect Politics</span> and the <span>Economy</span>?’</span> SSRN Electronic Journal. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.1942198">https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.1942198</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-bedoya2021" class="csl-entry">
Bedoya Dorado, Christian, and Juan David Peláez León. 2021. <span>‘Los Trabajos En La <span>Gig Economy</span>: Una Mirada Desde La Precarización Laboral’</span>. <em>Revista Lumen Gentium</em> 5 (1): 84–99. <a href="https://doi.org/10.52525/lg.v5n1a6">https://doi.org/10.52525/lg.v5n1a6</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-borjas2020" class="csl-entry">
Borjas, George. 2020. <em>Labor <span>Economics</span></em>. <span>McGraw Hill</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-brozova2015" class="csl-entry">
Brožová, Dagmar. 2015. <span>‘Modern <span>Labour Economics</span>: <span>The Neoclassical Paradigm</span> with <span>Institutional Content</span>’</span>. <em>Procedia Economics and Finance</em> 30: 50–56. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/s2212-5671(15)01254-x">https://doi.org/10.1016/s2212-5671(15)01254-x</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-bunyan2014" class="csl-entry">
Bunyan, John. 2014. <em>The Pilgrim’s Progress</em>. <span>Desiring God</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-dik2007" class="csl-entry">
Dik, B. J., and R. D. Duffy. 2007. <span>‘Calling and <span>Vocation</span> at <span>Work</span>’</span>. <em>The Counseling Psychologist</em> 37 (3): 424–50. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0011000008316430">https://doi.org/10.1177/0011000008316430</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-gorz1997" class="csl-entry">
Gorz, André. 1997. <em>Metamorfosis Del Trabajo</em>. <span>Editorial Sistema</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-kaltenbrunner2018" class="csl-entry">
Kaltenbrunner, Annina, and Juan Pablo Painceira. 2018. <span>‘Financierización En <span>América Latina</span>: Implicancias de La Integración Financiera Subordinada’</span>. In <em>Estudios Sobre Financierización En <span>América Latina</span></em>, edited by Martín Abeles, Esteban Pérez, and Sergio Valdecantos, 33–67. <span>CEPAL</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lopez_oneto2016" class="csl-entry">
López Oneto, M. 2016. <span>‘Las Metamorfosis Del Trabajo: Del Trabajo Al Empleo (Notas de Lectura Para Una Reconstrucción Histórica-Conceptual Del Trabajo)’</span>. <em>Revista Chilena de Derecho Del Trabajo y de La Seguridad Social</em> 5 (9). <a href="https://doi.org/10.5354/0719-7551.2014.42643">https://doi.org/10.5354/0719-7551.2014.42643</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-luther1957" class="csl-entry">
Luther, M. 1957. <em>Luther’s <span>Works</span>: <span>Career</span> of the <span>Reformer</span></em>. Edited by H. Green. Vol. 1. <span>Fortress Press</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-marx1992" class="csl-entry">
Marx, Karl. 1992. <em>Early <span>Writings</span></em>. <span>Penguin</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-neffa2011" class="csl-entry">
Neffa, J. 2011. <span>‘Políticas de Empleo: Dimensiones Conceptuales y Diversos Componentes’</span>. <em>Empleo, Desempleo y Políticas de Empleo 1853-0257</em>, 1–100.
</div>
<div id="ref-neffa2014" class="csl-entry">
Neffa, J., D. Panigo, P. Pérez, and J. Persia. 2014. <em>Actividad, Empleo y Desempleo. <span>Conceptos</span> y Definiciones</em>. <span>CEIL-CONICET</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-phelps1968" class="csl-entry">
Phelps, E. S. 1968. <span>‘Money-<span>Wage Dynamics</span> and <span>Labor</span>-<span>Market Equilibrium</span>’</span>. <em>Journal of Political Economy</em> 76 (4, Part 2): 678–711. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/259438">https://doi.org/10.1086/259438</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-staley1965" class="csl-entry">
Staley, E., and R. Morse. 1965. <em>Modern <span>Small Industry</span> for <span>Developing Countries</span></em>. <span>McGraw Hill</span>.
</div>
<div id="ref-vercherand2014" class="csl-entry">
Vercherand, J. 2014. <span>‘The <span>Neoclassical Model</span> of the <span>Labour Market</span>’</span>. In <em>The Labour Market and Economic Theory</em>, 53–74. <span>Palgrave Macmillan UK</span>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1057/9781137373618_3">https://doi.org/10.1057/9781137373618_3</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-weber2001" class="csl-entry">
Weber, Max. 2001. <em>The <span>Protestant Ethic</span> and the <span>Spirit</span> of <span>Capitalism</span></em>. <span>Routledge</span>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>«Religion is the sigh of the oppressed creature, the heart of a heartless world and the soul of soulless conditions. It is the opium of the people. The abolition of religion as the illusory happiness of the people is the demand for their real happiness» <span class="citation" data-cites="marx1992">(Marx 1992, 244)</span>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>As Gorz explains: «Unlike the utopians, whose visions of the future society express ideals derived from ethical demands, Marx wants to demonstrate that communism does not need to pre-exist in the consciousness of the proletarians to be realised: it is the “movement of the real” itself […] Each individual will be “as an individual”, with the mediation of voluntary collaboration, master of the totality of the productive forces, his “work” will become his “autonomous activity” (<em>Selbsttätigkeit</em>) of the “total individual”» <span class="citation" data-cites="gorz1997">(Gorz 1997, 42–43)</span>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Luther expressed it thus: «Nevertheless, I shall prove the thesis for the sake of those who are misinformed, first from the Greek word <em>metanoeite</em> itself, which means “repent”: and could be translated more exactly by the Latin <em>trasmentamini</em>, which means <em>“assume another mind and feeling, recover one’s senses, make transition from one state of mind to another, have a change of spirit”</em>; so that those who hitherto have been aware of earthly matters may now know the spiritual, as the Apostle (Paul) says in Romans 12:2, <em>“Be transformed by the renewal of your mind.”</em> By this recovery of one’s senses it happens that the sinner has a change of heart and hates his sin» <span class="citation" data-cites="luther1957">(Luther 1957)</span>.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <guid>https://normansimonr.github.io/consultancy_website/posts/work_ethic/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
